<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>blog of bhch</title><link href="https://bhch.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://bhch.github.io/feeds/atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://bhch.github.io/</id><updated>2017-04-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><entry><title>Fix the pip error: Couldn't find a version that satisfies the requirement</title><link href="https://bhch.github.io/posts/2017/04/fix-the-pip-error-couldnt-find-a-version-that-satisfies-the-requirement/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-04-13T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>bhch</name></author><id>tag:bhch.github.io,2017-04-13:posts/2017/04/fix-the-pip-error-couldnt-find-a-version-that-satisfies-the-requirement/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;To skip the background and go to the solution, &lt;a href="#solution"&gt;click here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was working on a server recently and I had to install some Python packages. 
What better way to install Python packages other than by using &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt;. So, I wrote 
this command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;pip install -r requirements.txt
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;But, it spat out the following error:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could not find a version that satisfies the requirement &lt;package-name&gt; (from versions:)
No matching distribution found for &lt;package-name&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried again, didn't work. Then I searched Google for some help. I found a 
couple of similar questions asked on Stack Overflow. I followed advice there, but 
that didn't help me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kept &lt;em&gt;searching the internet&lt;/em&gt; for almost 2 hours, when I finally gave up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next day, I had to get the server running. So, I decided to install the packages 
from source. I intended to use &lt;code&gt;wget&lt;/code&gt; to download the packages from PyPi. But, 
it gave me a &lt;code&gt;403 Forbidden&lt;/code&gt; error. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried downloading with &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt;, but the files it &lt;em&gt;saved&lt;/em&gt; were invalid. It just 
created empy &lt;code&gt;tar.gz&lt;/code&gt; files without actually downloading them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also tried changning my server's DNS. Nothing worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I though &lt;em&gt;"Let's just see if I can even visit PyPi webpage from this server"&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;curl https://pypi.python.org

The requestors Network has been blacklisted due to excessive request volume. 
If you are a hosting customer, please contact your hosting company&lt;span class="err"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;s support. 
If you are the hosting company, please contact infrastructure-staff@python.org to resolve
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The output above shows that my server's IP was blacklisted by &lt;a href="https://python.org"&gt;https://python.org&lt;/a&gt;. 
Well, obviously, because my hosting provier was running many servers 
(virtual servers) behind a single IP. This explains the reason for getting blacklisted. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Solution&lt;a name="solution"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First lets' see the solutions that I tried and &lt;strong&gt;didn't work&lt;/strong&gt; for me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Changing DNS resolver of my server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reconfiguring SSL, reinstalling CA certificates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downloading packages using &lt;code&gt;wget&lt;/code&gt;. (Got 403 Forbidden error)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Downloading packages using &lt;code&gt;curl&lt;/code&gt;. (It just created invalid tarball files, instead of actually downloading them)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since, all this was happening because &lt;a href="https://python.org"&gt;https://python.org&lt;/a&gt; has blacklisted the IP 
of my hosting provider, the obvious solution was to make &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; install via a proxy. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplying a proxy address to &lt;code&gt;pip&lt;/code&gt; is easy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;pip install -r requirements.txt --proxy address:port
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;To find proxies, just &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=proxy+list"&gt;search Google for proxy list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Getting started with Data Science and Machine Learning in Python</title><link href="https://bhch.github.io/posts/2017/03/getting-started-with-data-science-and-machine-learning-in-python/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-03-23T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>bhch</name></author><id>tag:bhch.github.io,2017-03-23:posts/2017/03/getting-started-with-data-science-and-machine-learning-in-python/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been a long time since I first thought about learning Data Science and 
Machine Learning. If you, too, want to get started with ML, let's embark on this 
journey together. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will share how I plan to get started with ML. This isn't supposed 
to be a &lt;em&gt;guide&lt;/em&gt;, per se. I'm also a beginner in this, you know. Feel free to 
leave suggestions in comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Do you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need Math?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you're wondering if you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need to know the ML related Math that
bad before doing some actual ML stuff, then no, you don't. I believe in  &lt;em&gt;learn
as you go&lt;/em&gt; approach. Don't get me wrong, I like Math (espesially  Functions and
Limits). But I want to  get started quickly and will learn the necessary Math
when I'll need it.  Here's a post on R-bloggers &amp;mdash;  &lt;a href="http://www.r-bloggers.com/the-real-prerequisite-for-machine-learning-isnt-math-its-data-analysis/"&gt;The real prerequisite
for machine learning isn't math, it's data analysis&lt;/a&gt;  and here's another on
Cross Validated &amp;mdash;  &lt;a href="http://stats.stackexchange.com/questions/40808/is-a-strong-background-in-maths-a-total-requisite-for-ml"&gt;Is a strong background in maths a total requisite for
ML?&lt;/a&gt; that you should read.  Both of these posts present pretty solid
discussions why Math isn't an outright  necessity for ML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Installing packages&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before installing anything, it would be a better if you create a virtualenv 
just for Machine Learning. And then install the following packages in that 
virtualenv.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IPython:&lt;/strong&gt;
 The &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; IDE for scientific computing.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Numpy:&lt;/strong&gt;
 For array computing, also, numpy arrays are awesome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pandas:&lt;/strong&gt;
 For data manipulation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Matplotlib:&lt;/strong&gt;
 For data visualization &lt;em&gt;i.e.&lt;/em&gt; plotting graphs, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scipy:&lt;/strong&gt;
 For scientific computing. Also, many other packages listed here require this.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scikit-learn:&lt;/strong&gt;
 For Machine Learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scrapy:&lt;/strong&gt;
 For web scraping. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BeautifulSoup:&lt;/strong&gt;
 For web scraping and parsing,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requests:&lt;/strong&gt;
 It's like urllib but &lt;a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/14804320/1925257"&gt;far better&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install, just copy the following command and run it in your terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="nv"&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;pip install numpy scipy matplotlib ipython jupyter pandas scikit-learn Scrapy beautifulsoup4 requests
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h1&gt;Now what?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, we'll need to read through the &lt;em&gt;Gettings started&lt;/em&gt; docs of the above 
libraries. However, I plan to do things in the following order:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Web scraping (requests, beautifulsoup, scrapy).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data structuring and manipulation (pandas).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data visualisation (numpy, matplotlib).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine learning (scikit-learn).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the above order is pretty good because learning curve isn't very steep 
right from the start. I've had some experience with web scraping before, so it 
should be relatively easier to start with that instead of directly getting into 
ML. Think of it as &lt;em&gt;paving your way into ML&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a future blog post, I plan to share the first web scraping project that I will 
do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until next time.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Hello, World!</title><link href="https://bhch.github.io/posts/2017/03/hello-world/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-03-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><author><name>bhch</name></author><id>tag:bhch.github.io,2017-03-20:posts/2017/03/hello-world/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The mandatory first post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still remember the day when I first decided to learn programming. I was so 
sure of which language I will be learning. The &lt;em&gt;inspiration&lt;/em&gt; to learn Python as 
my first programming language came when I was watching the film 
&lt;em&gt;The Social Network&lt;/em&gt;. In a scene, Mark Zuckerberg mentions 
&lt;em&gt;"... python webserver..."&lt;/em&gt;. Then I went on to search &lt;em&gt;"python"&lt;/em&gt; on Google. 
I read about Python on Wikipedia and other online resources. I was really 
fascinated by the number of applications this language had. Plus, the name is 
so &lt;em&gt;cool&lt;/em&gt; &amp;mdash; Python. It bears an air of mystery about itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the first line of code I ever wrote, and perhaps you did too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Hello, World!&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary></entry></feed>